Finding Aid for Rackham Student Government (University of Michigan) Records, 1948-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rackham Student Government (University of Michigan) records 1948-2001, 1967-2001
Rackham Student Government (University of Michigan)
4 linear feet
87281 Bimu F13 2
The Rackham Student Government facilitates student-faculty communication, provides funding for student activities, and appoints graduate-student representatives to university committees. The organization has operated under several different, earlier titles, including the Graduate Student Council and Graduate Assembly. This record group includes minutes, grant requests, correspondence, reports, and publications.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received from Rackham Student Government (donor no. 5846 ) in 1976 and 2005.
The record group is open without restriction.
When the Graduate Student Council (GSC) was founded on March 30, 1938, it was the first council of its kind at an American university. The GSC's mandate was to coordinate graduate-student activities, especially in regard to academics, student organizations, and housing. Forty-seven representatives gathered in the Horace H. Rackham Building for the council's first meeting in November 1938.
The council's earliest activities included faculty/student mixers, student dances, and a study of the language skills required by doctoral programs. In 1954, the council updated its constitution, and revised its bylaws.
In the 1960s, the council further revised its constitution and conducted a study of the Selective Service System. Student finances were a major concern for the council as it sought to lower fees associated with tuition, housing, and parking. Special committees addressed library services, testing in foreign-language classes, and the high cost of textbooks. The council also produced a handbook for graduate students.
On March 29, 1967, the Graduate Student Council passed a new constitution, inspired by a 1966 report by Vice President for Student Affairs Robert Knauss called "The Role of the Student in University Affairs." Seeking a more influential role for students in the "decision-making" of the university, the Graduate Student Council replaced itself with Graduate Assembly. In contrast to the GSC, which gave faculty members the ability to fill vacancies for up to one year, the Graduate Assembly was fully elected by graduate students (though faculty members were still allowed to make one-month appointments).
Graduate Assembly addressed issues similar to those formerly administered by the council, including the perennial concern of student fees. In 1970, the assembly created new regulations for student organizations, which set rules for membership, official recognition, activity planning, publicity, and the use of university facilities.
On March 30, 1971, the Central Student Judiciary, the judicial body of the campus-wide Student Government Council, found the assembly in violation of its own constitution, ruling that it had failed its mission to represent the genuine needs and interests of the graduate community. Meanwhile, elections on March 31, 1971, installed officers for a new Rackham Student Government whose constitution gave them control of Graduate Assembly's funding and facilities. Dismissing Graduate Assembly's claim that the Student Government Council did not have jurisdiction over them, on April 9, 1971, the Central Student Judiciary declared Graduate Assembly dissolved. The newly elected Rackham Student Government (RSG) thereby became the representative body of the graduate community.
Most of the issues addressed by the RSG during the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s were the same as those of its predecessors: tuition fees, housing costs, sexual harassment, and representation on committees. Like GA, the RSG provided funding for student organization activities and issued resolutions in response to political issues and events, including the Vietnam War, the Kent State shootings, and apartheid in South Africa. The RSG also spoke out about affirmative action and alleged activities of the Central Intelligence Agency on the University of Michigan campus.
____________________________
Sources Consulted Note
University of Michigan Library Clippings File, Box #30, Folders:
"Michigan, University Graduate School, 1938-1940"
"Michigan, University Graduate School, 1954-"
Michigan Daily articles:
"Assembly replaces GSC; Plan new representation," March 30, 1967
"CSJ to rule on GA case," March 26, 1971
"In defense of Graduate Assembly," March 27, 1971
"Concerned grads focus on Rackham proposal," March 28, 1971
"Rackham Student Government," March 28, 1971
"CSJ declares GA unrepresentative," March 31, 1971
"GA claims legitimacy despite CSJ findings," April 3, 1971
"CSJ declares GA dissolved, freezes all funds, assets," April 9, 1971
"New Graduate Assembly sought," September 30, 1971.
The Rackham Student Government record group consists of minutes, grant proposals, correspondence, publications, and reports. The record group is divided into four series: Minutes and Supporting Materials, Elections, Grant Requests, and Topical Files. All series are arranged chronologically, except the Topical Files series, which is arranged alphabetically.
Subjects:
Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; University of Michigan. Graduate Assembly.; University of Michigan. Graduate Student Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; Rackham Student Government (University of Michigan)
- Minutes and Supporting Materials 1950-1999
  The Minutes and Supporting Materials series (1.6 linear feet) covers the years 1950 to 1999, and includes minutes of the Graduate Student Council, Graduate Assembly, and Rackham Student Government meetings. Supporting materials include memoranda, correspondence, resolutions, and officers' personal notes. Researchers should note that the other series in this record group also contain documents and materials from these meetings.
  - 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989 (Box 2)
  - 1990 (Box 2)
  - 1991 (Box 2)
  - 1992 (Box 2)
  - 1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994 (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1998 (Box 2)
  - 1999 (Box 2)
- Elections 1972-1999
  The Elections (.2 linear feet) series spans the years 1972 to 1999, but the bulk of materials relate to the periods 1972-1973 and 1989-1999. The series includes materials about specific contests, including correspondence, statements by candidates, procedures, and election results.
  - General 1977, 1980, 1990, undated (Box 2)
  - 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1984 Winter Challenge (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989 (Box 2)
  - 1997 (Box 2)
  - 1998 (Box 2)
  - 1999 (Box 2)
- Grant Requests 1971-1980
  The Grant Requests (.7 linear feet) series contains proposal forms and supporting material from student groups and organizations seeking funding during 1971-1980. Some groups provided extensive background material in order to improve their chances of securing funding for their project or event. Political and ethnic student organizations are particularly well represented. Most of the requests contained in this subseries date from the years 1986 to 1998.
  - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989 (Box 2)
  - 1991, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1993 (Box 3)
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - Data Analysis 1988-1996 (Box 3)
  - Fee Changes 1979, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Fund Transfers 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Policy 1981, 1990, 1996 (Box 3)
- Topical Files 1961-1998
  The Topical Files (1.5 linear feet) series covers several issues related to student life from 1961 to 1998, including housing, tuition costs, parking, and teaching assistantships. Researchers may find the folders "Introductory Information, 1980-1985" and "Introductory Packet, 1997" useful as summaries of the RSG's mission and responsibilities. The folder "Constitution and Bylaws" contains copies of the constitution of 1954 and later revisions, and of by-laws from 1971 and later revisions. This series also includes a copy of "Report on the Role of the Student in University Affairs," by Robert Knauss.
  - 1954-1997
    - General 1980, 1982, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Ad Hoc Tenure Committee 1968 (Box 3)
    - Child Care Oversight Committee 1997 (Box 3)
    - Committee Applications 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1954, 1962, 1967, 1971, 1973, 1984, 1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Council of Graduate and Professional Students (Box 3)
    - General 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Lisa Montney 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Fee and Enrollment Policies 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Financial Reports 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Federation 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Student Associateship Program 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Housing
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1967 (Box 3)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 3)
      - Northwood Terrace Association Rent Dispute 1967 (Box 3)
      - Housing Orientation Officer, Applications 1975 (Box 3)
    - Information Technology Division, Computer Use Policy 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Introductory Information [to Rackham Student Government] 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Introductory Packet [to Rackham Student Government] 1997 (Box 4)
    - Language Requirements for Graduate Students 1962, 1964, 1966, 1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan Student Assembly, Correspondence 1982, 1989-1991, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Models of Student Government (compiled by Marc Lambert) 1997 (Box 4)
    - Motor Vehicles at the University of Michigan (Students) 1965 [Report created by Institute of Social Research] (Box 4)
    - National Association of Graduate-Professional Students (Box 4)
    - General, 1987(?) 1990 (Box 4)
    - Beginners Guides 1994 (Box 4)
    - Orientation Packet 1997 (Box 4)
    - Protests
      - Civil Rights and Financial Aid 1987 (Box 4)
      - Kent State Resolution 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Publications 1949, 1957, 1961, 1973, 1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Publications Rackham Student News, 1975-1980 (Box 4)
    - RSG Members 1948-1974, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Report on the Role of the Student in University Affairs 1966 (Box 4)
      [This copy of the report was reproduced by the Graduate Assembly]
    - Report on the Role of the Student in University Affairs, Changes in Regents' Bylaws 1967, 1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Selective Service 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) Appointments 1971 (Box 4)
    - Student Judiciary 1970 (Box 4)
    - Student Organization Account Services, Depository Contracts 1997-1999 (Box 4)
    - Student Organizations, General 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Student Organizations, Directory 1974 (Box 4)
    - Teaching Assistants (Box 4)
    - Payment 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Survey 1970 (Box 4)
    - Tax Waiver as Taxable Income 1984 (Box 4)